America's favorite pie is?
ما هي الفطيرة المفضلة عند الشعب الأمريكي؟
Audience: Apple. Kenneth Cukier: Apple. Of course it is.
الجمهور: فطيرة التفاح. كينيث كوكير: فطيرة التفاح، بالطبع.
How do we know it?
كيف عرفنا ذلك؟
Because of data.
طبعاً بفضل البيانات.
You look at supermarket sales.
ألقوا نظرة على مبيعات مراكز التسوق الكبرى.
You look at supermarket sales of 30-centimeter pies
انظروا الى مبيعات الفطائر المثلجة بحجم ٣٠ سنتيمتر
The majority of the sales are apple.
أغلبية المبيعات من منتجات التفاح.
But then supermarkets started selling
لكن فيما بعد، اتجهت هذه المراكز إلى بيع
smaller, 11-centimeter pies,
فطائر أصغر حجماً بحجم 11 سنتيمتر
and suddenly, apple fell to fourth or fifth place.
وفجأة تراجعت منتجات التفاح إلى المرتبة الرابعة أو الخامسة
Why? What happened?
لماذا؟ ماذا حدث؟
Okay, think about it.
حسنا، لنفكر في الأمر.
When you buy a 30-centimeter pie,
عندما تشتري فطيرة بقياس 30 سنتمتر،
the whole family has to agree,
يجب أن تجمع كل الأسرة على نفس الاختيار،
and apple is everyone's second favorite.
والتفاح هو الخيار المفضل الثاني عند الجميع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But when you buy an individual 11-centimeter pie,
لكن عندما تشتري فطائر بقياس 11 سنتمتر فردية،
you can buy the one that you want.
يمكنك شراء ما تفضله أنت.
You can get your first choice.
أي يمكنك أن تشتري اختيارك المفضل.
You have more data.
بهذا تملك بيانات أكثر.
You can see something
بإمكانك رؤية أمور
that you couldn't see
لم تكن تراها في السابق
when you only had smaller amounts of it.
حين كان لديك كمية أقل من البيانات.
Now, the point here is that more data
المقصود بهذا هو أن كثرة البيانات
doesn't just let us see more,
لا تسمح لنا فقط برؤية أشياء أكثر
more of the same thing we were looking at.
عن ما نراه.
More data allows us to see new.
بل أكثر من ذلك، فهي تعطينا رؤية جديدة.
It allows us to see better.
تعطينا رؤية أفضل.
It allows us to see different.
تعطينا منظوراً مختلفاً للأمور.
In this case, it allows us to see
و في هذه الحالة،
not apple.
وهي ليست فطائر التفاح.
Now, you probably all have heard the term big data.
أظن أن الجميع هنا قد سمعوا بمصطلح "البيانات الضخمة"
In fact, you're probably sick of hearing the term
أظنكم قد سئمتم من سماع مصطلح "البيانات الضخمة"
It is true that there is a lot of hype around the term,
صحيح أنه أثار ضجة كبيرة كمصطلح،
and that is very unfortunate,
وهذا أمرٌ مؤسف،
because big data is an extremely important tool
لأن البيانات الضخمة تعد أداةً مهمةً جداً
by which society is going to advance.
لمساعدة المجتمع على التقدم.
In the past, we used to look at small data
ففي السابق، اعتدنا على رؤية بياناتٍ محدودةٍ
and think about what it would mean
ومحاولة فهم معناها
to try to understand the world,
في سبيل فهم العالم من خلالها،
and now we have a lot more of it,
أما الآن فلدينا فائض منها،
more than we ever could before.
أكثر من السابق بكثير.
What we find is that when we have
اكتشفنا أنه عند امتلاكنا بيانات ضخمة،
Big data is important, and big data is new,
فالبيانات الضخمة مهمة وحديثة العهد،
and when you think about it,
و عندما تفكر في هذا الأمر
the only way this planet is going to deal
ستجد بأنها الوسيلة الوحيدة التي ستمكن كوكبنا من التعامل مع تحدياته العالمية.
to feed people, supply them with medical care,
لتغذية الناس وإمدادهم بالعناية الطبية،
supply them with energy, electricity,
و إمدادهم بالطاقة والكهرباء،
and to make sure they're not burnt to a crisp
و حمايتهم من الدمار الشامل بسبب الاحتباس الحراري.
is because of the effective use of data.
وهذا بفضل الاستخدام الفعال للبيانات.
So what is new about big data? What is the big deal?
إذا ما الجديد في البيانات الضخمة؟ ما الأمر المهم؟
Well, to answer that question, let's think about
حسنا، للإجابة لهذا السؤال،
physically looked like in the past.
ظاهرياً في الماضي.
In 1908, on the island of Crete,
في 1908 في جزيرة كريت
archaeologists discovered a clay disc.
اكتشف علماء الآثار قرص من طين.
They dated it from 2000 B.C., so it's 4,000 years old.
يعود تاريخه الى 2000 قبل الميلاد. يبلغ عمره 4000 سنة.
Now, there's inscriptions on this disc,
توجد هناك نقوش على هذا القرص
but we actually don't know what it means.
لكننا لا نعرف معناها بعد.
It's a complete mystery, but the point is that
الأمر يشوبه غموض تام، لكن المهم هو
this is what information used to look like
ان المعلومات كانت على هذا الشكل
4,000 years ago.
منذ 4000 سنة.
This is how society stored
هكذا كان يوثق المجتمع
and transmitted information.
وينقل المعلومات.
Now, society hasn't advanced all that much.
أما الآن، فلم تتقدم المجتمعات كثيراً
We still store information on discs,
فما زلنا نخزن المعلومات على الأقراص،
but now we can store a lot more information,
لكن حالياً يمكننا أن نخزن كماً أكبر من المعلومات،
more than ever before.
أكثر من قبل.
Searching it is easier. Copying it easier.
البحث والنسخ صارا أسهل.
Sharing it is easier. Processing it is easier.
و كذلك المشاركة والمعالجة.
And what we can do is we can reuse this information
باستطاعتنا إعادة استخدام هذه المعلومات
for uses that we never even imagined
لاستعمالات لم نكن نتخيلها
when we first collected the data.
عندما كنا نجمع المعلومات لأول مرة.
In this respect, the data has gone
في هذه الحالة، انتقلت البيانات
from a stock to a flow,
من التخزين إلى تدفق للمعلومات،
from something that is stationary and static
من شيءٍ جامدٍ وراكد،
to something that is fluid and dynamic.
إلى آخر سلسٍ ومتحرك.
There is, if you will, a liquidity to information.
بل و يمكننا أن نصف المعلومات بالسيولة.
The disc that was discovered off of Crete
فالقرص الذي اكتُشف في كريت
that's 4,000 years old, is heavy,
والذي يبلغ عمره 4000 سنة ثقيل،
it doesn't store a lot of information,
لا يمكنه تخزين كمٍّ كبيرٍ من المعلومات،
and that information is unchangeable.
و هذه المعلومات غير قابلة للتغيير.
By contrast, all of the files
بالمقابل، فجميع الملفات
that Edward Snowden took
التي أخذها إدوارد سنودن،
from the National Security Agency in the United States
من وكالة الأمن القومي في الولايات المتحدة
fits on a memory stick
يمكن تخزينها على ذاكرة محمولة،
the size of a fingernail,
بحجم الإظفر.
and it can be shared at the speed of light.
كما يمكن مشاركة هذه المعلومات بلمح البصر.
More data. More.
الكثير والكثير من البيانات.
Now, one reason why we have so much data in the world today
أحد أسباب وجود هذا الكم من البيانات
is we are collecting things
وهو أننا نخزن أموراً
that we've always collected information on,
كنا دائماً نجمع معلومات عنها،
but another reason why is we're taking things
وسبب آخر لهذا، أننا نأخذ أشياء
that have always been informational
كانت دوماً مليئة بالمعلومات
but have never been rendered into a data format
ولكنها لم تحول إلى صيغة البيانات
and we are putting it into data.
ومع ذلك نضعها مع البيانات.
Think, for example, the question of location.
على سبيل المثال، مسألة المكان.
Take, for example, Martin Luther.
مثلاً مارتن لوثر.
If we wanted to know in the 1500s
لو أننا كنا في القرن السادس عشر وأردنا معرفة مكان مارتن لوثر
we would have to follow him at all times,
كان علينا أن نتعقبه بشكل دائم و نحن نحمل قلم ودواة حبر ونسجل مكانه،
but now think about what it looks like today.
أما اليوم انظروا كيف اختلفت الأمور
You know that somewhere,
تعلمون بأنه في مكان ما
probably in a telecommunications carrier's database,
لعل في قاعدة بيانات شركة اتصالات
there is a spreadsheet or at least a database entry
يوجد هناك مدخل او جدول في قاعدة بيانات
that records your information
التي تسجل معلوماتك
of where you've been at all times.
حول مكانك في كل وقت
If you have a cell phone,
اذا كان لديك هاتف خلوي
and that cell phone has GPS, but even if it doesn't have GPS,
و كان مزودا بنظام تحديد المواقع او لا
it can record your information.
فيمكنه تسجيل معلوماتك
In this respect, location has been datafied.
اذن, فقد تم تسجيل معومات مكانك
Now think, for example, of the issue of posture,
و الآن فكر في وضعيتك
the way that you are all sitting right now,
وضعية جلوسك الآن
the way that you sit,
كيفية جلوسك
the way that you sit, the way that you sit.
الطريفة التي تجلس فيها انت و انت
It's all different, and it's a function of your leg length
كلها مختلفة بسبب طول قدمك
and your back and the contours of your back,
و ظهرك و وضعية ظهرك
and if I were to put sensors, maybe 100 sensors
لو وضعت مئة جهاز استشعار
into all of your chairs right now,
في كل الكراسي الآن
I could create an index that's fairly unique to you,
لاستطعت رسم مخطط خاص بك
sort of like a fingerprint, but it's not your finger.
و كأنه بصمتك , و لكن ليس بصمة اصبعك
So what could we do with this?
اذن ماذا استطيع ان افعل مع هذا؟
Researchers in Tokyo are using it
يستخدم الباحثون هذه الخاصية في طوكيو
as a potential anti-theft device in cars.
كجهاز كامن ضد السرقة في السيارات
The idea is that the carjacker sits behind the wheel,
عندما يجلس السارق خلف المقود
tries to stream off, but the car recognizes
و يحاول الانطلاق, عندها تتعرف السيارة
that a non-approved driver is behind the wheel,
على ان الجالس لم يتم التعرف عليه
and maybe the engine just stops, unless you
و عندها ينطفئ المحرك
type in a password into the dashboard
الا اذا ادخلت الرقم السري في لوحة القيادة
to say, "Hey, I have authorization to drive." Great.
مثلا "مرحبا, لدي الصلاحية في القيادة"
What if every single car in Europe
ماذا لو كل سيارة في اروبا
had this technology in it?
كانت تمتلك هذه التقنية؟
What could we do then?
ماذا كنا نستطيع ان نفعله؟
Maybe, if we aggregated the data,
لو اجمعنا البيانات
maybe we could identify telltale signs
لاستطعنا ان نتعرف على اشارات المؤشر
that best predict that a car accident
و يعمل ايضا كافضل جهاز يتوقع حدوث اصطدام
is going to take place in the next five seconds.
في الخمس ثوان المقبلة
And then what we will have datafied
اذن, ستبين البيانات
is driver fatigue,
بأن السائق مرهق
and the service would be when the car senses
و ستفعل الخدمة عندما تستشعر السيارة
that the person slumps into that position,
بأن السائق يبدأ بالارهاق
automatically knows, hey, set an internal alarm
عندها ستفعل نظام الانذار الداخلي
that would vibrate the steering wheel, honk inside
التي تبدأ بهز المقود و الصفير
to say, "Hey, wake up,
اشارة للسائق بأن يستيقظ
pay more attention to the road."
و ان يراقب الطريق اكثر
These are the sorts of things we can do
هذه الأمور التي باستطاعتنا فعله
when we datafy more aspects of our lives.
عندما نستجمع معلومات اكثر عن حياتنا
So what is the value of big data?
اذن, ما هي فائدة هذا الكم من البيانات؟
Well, think about it.
حسنا, لننظر في الأمر
You have more information.
لديك كم اكبر من المعلومات
You can do things that you couldn't do before.
تستطيع فعل امور اكثر من ذي قبل
One of the most impressive areas
من اكثر المجالات المذهلة
where this concept is taking place
التي تعمل فيها هذه الخاصية
is in the area of machine learning.
هو مجال التعلم الآلي
Machine learning is a branch of artificial intelligence,
التعلم الآلي هو فرع من الذكاء الاصطناعي
which itself is a branch of computer science.
و الذي في ذاته فرع من علوم الحاسبات
The general idea is that instead of
بشكل عام تكون الفكرة
instructing a computer what do do,
انه بدل من امر الحاسوب بالعمل
we are going to simply throw data at the problem
ببساطة سندخل معلومات حول المشكلة
and tell the computer to figure it out for itself.
و نخبر الحاسبة بحل المشكلة بنفسها
And it will help you understand it
ستساعدك هذه العملية في فهم المشكلة
by seeing its origins.
في النظر في اصلها
In the 1950s, a computer scientist
في الخمسينيات, كان هنالك عالم في الحاسبات
at IBM named Arthur Samuel liked to play checkers,
في شركة (IBM) يعرف بـ آرثر سامويل كان يحب
so he wrote a computer program
الشطرنج, فصنع برنامجا
so he could play against the computer.
يستطيع فيها اللعب ضد الحاسبة
He played. He won.
لعب ففاز
because the computer only knew
لأن الحاسبة كانت تعرف
what a legal move was.
الخطوات القانونية في اللعبة
Arthur Samuel knew something else.
ولكن سامويل كان يعرف امرا آخر
Arthur Samuel knew strategy.
كان يعرف الاستراتيجية
So he wrote a small sub-program alongside it
فصنع برنامجا ثانويا مع اللعبة
operating in the background, and all it did
يعمل خلف الكواليس
was score the probability
و كل ما كان يفعله هو حساب الاحتمالات
that a given board configuration would likely lead
انه اي لترتيب في اللعبة سيؤدي الى
to a winning board versus a losing board
الفوز ضد الخصم
after every move.
بعد كل حركة في اللعبة
He plays the computer. He wins.
لعب ضد الحاسبة ففاز
And then Arthur Samuel leaves the computer
بعدها ترك الحاسبة
to play itself.
لتكون خصم نفسها في اللعبة
It plays itself. It collects more data.
لعبت ضد نفسها و استجمعت بيانات اكثر
It collects more data. It increases the accuracy of its prediction.
اكتسبت بيانات اكثر و زادت في دقة توقعاتها
And then Arthur Samuel goes back to the computer
ثم رجع سامويل الى الحاسبة
and he plays it, and he loses,
و لعب ضد الحاسبة فخسر
and Arthur Samuel has created a machine
عندها صنع سامويل آلة فاقت قدرته
that surpasses his ability in a task that he taught it.
في المهمة التي علمها الى الحاسبة.
And this idea of machine learning
و بدأت فكرة التعليم الآلي
is going everywhere.
بالتوسع في كل مكان.
How do you think we have self-driving cars?
اذن كيف حصلنا على سيارة ذات السياقة الآلية
Are we any better off as a society
هل سنكون افضل كمجتمع واحد يعمل على
enshrining all the rules of the road into software?
ادخال المعلومات المرورية الى برنامج واحد؟
No. Memory is cheaper. No.
كلا. هل السبب في الخزن الرخيص؟ كلا.
Algorithms are faster. No. Processors are better. No.
في سرعة الخوارزميات؟ سرعة المعالجات؟ كلا
All of those things matter, but that's not why.
كلها مهمة الا انها ليست السبب.
It's because we changed the nature of the problem.
السبب هو اننا غيرنا طبيعة المشكلة.
We changed the nature of the problem from one
غيرنا طبيعة المشكلة الى
in which we tried to overtly and explicitly
صورة نعمل فيها بجهد
explain to the computer how to drive
على تعليم الحاسبة كيفية السياقة
to one in which we say,
في برنامج نقول له:
"Here's a lot of data around the vehicle.
"هذه معلومات حول السيارة"
You figure it out.
انت اكتشف الأمر لوحدك
You figure it out that that is a traffic light,
انت اكتشف اين اشارة المرور.
that that traffic light is red and not green,
و ان الاشارة حمراء و ليست خضراء
that that means that you need to stop
و التي تعني التوقف
and not go forward."
و ليس الحركة.
Machine learning is at the basis
التعليم الآلي هو الأساس
of many of the things that we do online:
لكثير من الأمور التي نفعلها على النت
search engines,
مثل محركات البحث
Amazon's personalization algorithm,
و الخوارزميات المخصصة لموقع آمازون
computer translation,
و ترجمة الحاسبة
voice recognition systems.
و انظمة التعرف الصوتي.
Researchers recently have looked at
بدأ الباحثون مؤخرا في دراسة
the question of biopsies,
التحليلات النسيجية
cancerous biopsies,
و التحليلات السرطانية
and they've asked the computer to identify
و طلبوا من الحاسبة التعرف على النتائج
by looking at the data and survival rates
من خلال حساب البيانات و احتمالية الشفاء
to determine whether cells are actually
لتحديد ان كانت فعلا
cancerous or not,
الخلايا سرطانية ام لا.
and sure enough, when you throw the data at it,
و بالتأكيد عند ادخال البيانات
through a machine-learning algorithm,
عن طريق خوارزميات في التعليم الآلي
the machine was able to identify
استطاعت الحاسبة في التعرف
the 12 telltale signs that best predict
على اثني عشر مؤشرا من التحليل
that this biopsy of the breast cancer cells
ان هذه الخلايا
are indeed cancerous.
هي بالفعل خلايا سرطانية.
The problem: The medical literature
كانت المشكلة ان المعلومات الطبية المتوفرة
only knew nine of them.
قد تعرفت على تسعة مؤشرات فقط
Three of the traits were ones
كانت هناك ثلاث مؤشرات
that people didn't need to look for,
لم يبحثها الأطباء
but that the machine spotted.
بينما اكتشفتها الحاسبة.
Now, there are dark sides to big data as well.
بالمقابل, هنالك جانب مظلم للبيانات الكبيرة
It will improve our lives, but there are problems
سوف تحسن طريقة حياتنا, لكن توجد هناك مشكلة
that we need to be conscious of,
يجب الحذر منها.
and the first one is the idea
اولها اننا
that we may be punished for predictions,
قد نُعاقب لهذه التنبؤات
that the police may use big data for their purposes,
لأن الشرطة قد تستخدم هذه الخاصية في عملها
a little bit like "Minority Report."
كما في فلم "تقرير الأقلية".
Now, it's a term called predictive policing,
يوجد الآن مصطلح يعرف بـ "الأمن التنبؤي"
or algorithmic criminology,
او "خوارزميات علم الجريمة"
and the idea is that if we take a lot of data,
و الفكرة هي عندما نأخذ مجموعة من البيانات
for example where past crimes have been,
مثلا مكان وقوع الجريمة
we know where to send the patrols.
سوف نعرف اين نرسل الدوريات
That makes sense, but the problem, of course,
هذا أمر منطقي, لكن المشكلة هي
is that it's not simply going to stop on location data,
ان النظام لن يتوقف عند معلومات الموقع
it's going to go down to the level of the individual.
و انما يبدأ بالبحث في معلومات الأفراد
Why don't we use data about the person's
مثلا المعلومات الشخصية عن الشخص
high school transcript?
في ايام دراسته في الثانوية
Maybe we should use the fact that
لعنا يجب دراسة وضع الشخص
they're unemployed or not, their credit score,
ان كان موظفا ام لا, و درجته الائتمانية
their web-surfing behavior,
و طريقة استخدامه للانترنت
whether they're up late at night.
هل الشخص يبقى مستيقظا لوقت متأخر
Their Fitbit, when it's able to identify biochemistries,
و معلومات نظامه الصحي و العقلي
will show that they have aggressive thoughts.
عندها سيتبين ان الفرد لديه افكار عدوانية.
We may have algorithms that are likely to predict
قد تكون لدينا خوارزميات تتنبأ
what we are about to do,
حول ما سنفعله بعد قليل
and we may be held accountable
و دراسة النتائج
before we've actually acted.
قبل الاقدام على الفعل.
Privacy was the central challenge
كان الخصوصية من اهم التحديات
in a small data era.
في مجال البيانات المحدودة.
In the big data age,
اما في عصر البيانات المفتوحة
the challenge will be safeguarding free will,
سوف يكون التحدي هو حماية الحرية الفردية
moral choice, human volition,
و القرارات الفردية و قوة الارادة
human agency.
و الكيان الفردي.
There is another problem:
توجد هناك مشكلة اخرى.
Big data is going to steal our jobs.
سوف تقوم هذه البيانات الضخمة بسرقة وظائفنا
Big data and algorithms are going to challenge
هذه البيانات الى جنب الخوارزميات سوف تقوم
white collar, professional knowledge work
بتحدي اعمالنا الاحترافية
in the 21st century
في القرن الواحد و العشرين
in the same way that factory automation
بنفس الطريقة التي قامت المصانع
and the assembly line
و الآليات
challenged blue collar labor in the 20th century.
بتحدي عمال الفحم في القرن العشرين.
Think about a lab technician
مثلا عامل فني في مختبر
who is looking through a microscope
الذي يقوم بالدراسة من خلال
at a cancer biopsy
النظر عبر المجهر في التحليلات
and determining whether it's cancerous or not.
و القرار ان كانت الخلايا سرطانية ام لا.
The person went to university.
في الواقع قد ذهب هذا الشخص الى الجامعة
The person buys property.
و قد يمتلك بيتا
He or she votes.
و يصوت في الانتخابات
He or she is a stakeholder in society.
و قد يكون من اصحاب المصالح في المجتمع
And that person's job,
فيصبح عمل هذا الشخص
as well as an entire fleet
و كثيرين من امثاله
of professionals like that person,
من المحترفين
is going to find that their jobs are radically changed
سوف يجدون ان اعمالهم قد تغيرت كليا
or actually completely eliminated.
او انتهت تماما.
Now, we like to think
و الآن علينا ان نفكر
that technology creates jobs over a period of time
بأن التكنولوجيا سوف تصنع وظائف جديدة
after a short, temporary period of dislocation,
خلال فترة زمنية قليلة
and that is true for the frame of reference
و التي سوف تمسنا
with which we all live, the Industrial Revolution,
و بعبارة اخرى انها ثورة صناعية اخرى
because that's precisely what happened.
و هذا بالفعل ما حدث.
But we forget something in that analysis:
و لكننا نسينا شيئا في هذا التحليل.
There are some categories of jobs
توجد هناك عدة اصناف من الوظائف
that simply get eliminated and never come back.
التي سوف تنتهي و لن تعود ابدا.
The Industrial Revolution wasn't very good
لم تكن الثورة الصناعية مثالية في واقعها
if you were a horse.
بانسبة للخيول مثلا.
So we're going to need to be careful
اذن علينا ان نكون اكثر حذرا
and take big data and adjust it for our needs,
و علينا ان نستفيد من البيانات بصورة تكمل
our very human needs.
الحاجات الانسانية
We have to be the master of this technology,
علينا ان نكون اسياد هذا التطور
not its servant.
و ليس عبيده.
We are just at the outset of the big data era,
نقف الآن على اعتاب هذا العصر المعلوماتي
and honestly, we are not very good
و بصراحة لسنا بارعين في هذا المجال
at handling all the data that we can now collect.
في تصنيف المعلومات التي نحصل عليها.
It's not just a problem for the National Security Agency.
ليت عائقا فقط لوكالة الأمن القومي.
Businesses collect lots of data, and they misuse it too,
يتم جمع كم هائل من البيانات و لكن لا تُستخدم بصورة صحيحة
and we need to get better at this, and this will take time.
علينا ان نطور انفسنا في هذا المجال و هذا يستغرق وقتا
It's a little bit like the challenge that was faced
يشبه هذا التحدي نفس التحدي
by primitive man and fire.
الذي واجهه الانسان البدائي مع النار.
This is a tool, but this is a tool that,
انها اداة, و لكننا
unless we're careful, will burn us.
ان استخدمناه بصورة خاطئة سوف تحرقنا.
Big data is going to transform how we live,
هذه البيانات سوف تغير طريقة معيشتنا
how we work and how we think.
و عملنا و طريقة تفكيرنا.
It is going to help us manage our careers
سوف تساعدنا في ادارة وظائفنا
and lead lives of satisfaction and hope
لنصنع حياة الرضا و الأمل
and happiness and health,
و السعادة و الصحة
but in the past, we've often looked at information technology
سابقا كنا ننظر الى تكنولوجيا المعلومات
and our eyes have only seen the T,
و لم نكن نرى فيها روحا
the technology, the hardware,
مجرد ادوات
because that's what was physical.
و هذا كان الواقع الملموس.
We now need to recast our gaze at the I,
اما الآن يجب ان نعيد النظر
the information,
لنرى الروح و ليس فقط الجسد
which is less apparent,
الذي هو اقل وضوحا
but in some ways a lot more important.
و لكن باتأكيد اكثر اهمية.
Humanity can finally learn from the information
استطاع البشر اخيرا ان يتعلم من المعلومات
that it can collect,
التي يستجمعها
as part of our timeless quest
جزءا من التساؤل الأزلي
to understand the world and our place in it,
حول مفهوم الحياة و الوجود
and that's why big data is a big deal.
و لهذا البيانات الكبيرة هي ذات اهمية كبيرة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)